<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case considered &amp; resolved: whether Mr. Brooks his pills to purge malignants were prescribed from ignorance, malice, or both, or, (Mr Tho. Brooks his inside turn'd outward). Wherein all godly, humble, and ingenious Christians, whether in a congregational way or other, are concerned, to inquire into the truth ... presented in generall to the inhabitants of Margarets New Fish-street, but more particularly for the consideration of himself, and those of his congregation ... also friendly advice to an unfriendly neighbour, desiring him for the time to come to abstain from reviling such persons as he never spake word to, nor they to him. / By Richard Parham, a parishoner of the said parish.</title>
            <author>Parham, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P356B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981689</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981689</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180294</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2824:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case considered &amp; resolved: whether Mr. Brooks his pills to purge malignants were prescribed from ignorance, malice, or both, or, (Mr Tho. Brooks his inside turn'd outward). Wherein all godly, humble, and ingenious Christians, whether in a congregational way or other, are concerned, to inquire into the truth ... presented in generall to the inhabitants of Margarets New Fish-street, but more particularly for the consideration of himself, and those of his congregation ... also friendly advice to an unfriendly neighbour, desiring him for the time to come to abstain from reviling such persons as he never spake word to, nor they to him. / By Richard Parham, a parishoner of the said parish.</title>
                  <author>Parham, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.A. for William Larnar at the Black-Moor's-head near Fleet-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpiece; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brooks, Thomas, 1608-1680. --  Cases considered and resolved.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Appointment, call, and election --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lay preaching --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:1"/>
            <p>THE CASE conſidered &amp; reſolved: VVhether Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> his Pills to purge Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants were preſcribed from Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Malice, or both?</p>
            <p>OR (Mr. <hi>Tho. Brooks</hi> his inſide turn'd outward:) WHEREIN All godly, humble, and ingenious Chriſtians, whether in a Congregational way or other, are concerned, to inquire into the truth of thoſe mens Commiſſions, who pretend themſelves to be Preachers of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Preſented in generall to the Inhabitants of <hi>Margarets</hi> New Fiſh-ſtreet, but more particularly for the conſideration of himſelf, and thoſe of his Congregation, to undeceive them of thoſe groſſe conceits that they may have of him, or he of himſelf, that he is appointed by Chriſt, and hath a Commiſſion to preach the Goſpel and Baptize.</p>
            <p>Alſo Friendly advice to an unfriendly Neighbour, deſiring him for the time to come to abſtain from reviling ſuch perſons as he never ſpake word to, nor they to him.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Parham,</hi> a Pariſhioner of the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 7.15, 20, 21.</hi>
               </bibl> Beware of falſe prophets which come to you in ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves: wherefore by their fruits ye ſhall know them; not every one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in heaven.</q>
            <p>Qui alterum incuſat probri, ipſum ſe intueri oportet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. A.</hi> for <hi>William Larnar</hi> at the Black Moor's head neer Fleet-Bridge. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:2"/>
            <head>To the impartiall Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have obſerved, that many times a good Cauſe ſuffers deeply through weak man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, when ſome there are who by the ſtrength of perſwaſive oratory, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died eloquent expreſſions, are able, and do commonly perſwade moſt of their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to believe any thing they tell them, though contrary to truth and reaſon.</p>
            <p>How prevailing a ſmooth and curious ſtile is to work on the affections, it cannot but be obvious to moſt; for, who is it that hath not obſerved divers, when reading of hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, nay and ſome of thoſe but fictions, have been drawn forth exceedingly both to hope and feare, to joy and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row accordingly as they have been variouſly inclined. Therfore, as from an untun'd Inſtrument, you will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect melodious muſick, ſo from an unlearned Pen you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not look for delightfull ſtraines, or poliſht lines. But ſuch as is tendred I deſire may have as friendly acceptance, and favourable conſtruction, as it is freely offered and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended: And if you find truth in the Diſcourſe, own it, though cloathed in rags: For certainly were there not an excellency in truth, none would be drawn to love and owne it on its own ſingle account.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe there are many pretenders to truth, and the wayes thereof, but it is with ſuch pretenders, as with thoſe that followed Chriſt for the loaves. How eaſie is it to find
<pb facs="tcp:180294:3"/>many men zealous to cry up truth, Ordinances, and the wayes of Chriſt, when a fat Parſonage, a Lecture, a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Congregation and ſome outward preferment comes in the cloſe. But how few, if any, think you, might we have to preach upon Chriſts allowance to his Apoſtles, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.3. <hi>And he ſaid unto them take nothing for your journey, neither ſtaves, neither ſcrip, neither bread, nor ſilver, neither two coats apiece.</hi> And upon the ſame allowance to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty he ſent to preach, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.4. <hi>Behold I ſend you forth as lambs amongſt wolves,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reader, it is not ſtrange to ſee (becauſe we have been foretold of it) that in the laſt dayes ſome ſhould ariſe that ſhould make merchandize of the word: And if ever there were a time to trie the ſpirits, certainly it is when that is fulfilled ſpoken by Chriſt himſelf, that <hi>many falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and deceive many, ſaying, lo here is Christ, lo there is Chriſt,</hi> but he bids us not believe them: and therefore if we are not willing to ſearch the Scriptures, to trie who are falſe, there is little hope we deſire thoſe that are true. And without controverſie the Devill is moſt like to deceive when he is transformed into an Angell of light.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould it be thought amiſſe, to queſtion the truth of the Miniſtery, and commiſſion of thoſe men that are continually queſtioning the truth of one anothers doctrine, not only in forms of worſhip, but in the very points of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſalvation? I need not inſtance in thoſe that preach univerſall Redemption, or Chriſt dying for all mankind without exception, how hotly are they oppoſed by thoſe that hold election and reprobation of particular perſons in anoaher ſenſe? Again, ſome that maintain childrens bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, others baptizing of believers only. Again, their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the manner of adminiſtration.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:3"/>
            <p>The cauſe of my ſetting pen to paper will be beſt ſeen in the following Diſcourſe, being briefly by Scripture to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask the proud boaſtings of a pretended Miniſter, whoſe laſt book many judicious men do conceive to be made up of ignorance of Chriſt and his wayes, and malice towards his Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that he and others of his ſtamp may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that there are divers in and about the City, that take good notice both of their doctrine and practiſe, that can ſo long as they are quiet ſuffer them to enjoy their freedome in the largeſt manner they can deſire, becauſe they plead it upon the account of conſcience; but if once they break the bounds of modeſty, in reviling and abuſing the Pariſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they can ſoon ſtrip them of their Canonicall Robes, and diſcover their deceit and hypocriſie to all the world.</p>
            <p>Again, that the growing greatneſſe of his ſelfe-conceit may be ſtopt; for if by our ſilence we ſhould grant him to be as he calls himſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> a Miniſter of the Spirit, we ſhould unavoidably be tyed up to his Dictates, as much as the Papiſts are to the Decrees of the Pope.</p>
            <p>Reader, be pleaſed to take notice what diſadvantages I have in preſenting this anſwer to his book, when the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman boaſteth in the nineth page thereof, <hi>that be hath ſpent more money at the Univerſity, in helps to learning, then ſeverall of the Pariſhioners are worth:</hi> And therefore if the truth of what is written cannot ſupqort it ſelf, it is like to have but little help from my Scholarſhip; not but that I have a high eſteem of learning, ſo long as it is uſed to its proper end, but not to have it uſed, as the Magitians did in <hi>Pharoahs</hi> Court, to delude both him and the people, onely be pleaſed to remember, that thoſe that were Miniſters of the Goſpell were fitted for the preaching of it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:180294:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180294:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180294:5"/>another manner then ſtudying at the Univerſity, as you may read <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. <hi>And they were all filled with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To conclude, in writing this piece I have to the beſt of my underſtanding caſt up the account, what it may amount to, and I hope I have not reckoned without my hoſt, which in ſhort the reward I expect for my time and paines is;</p>
            <p>Firſt, that divers ingenious, honeſt, and religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will accept it, although it add not ſo much to their underſtandings as the caſting a mite into a treaſury.</p>
            <p>Secondly I expect the ill will and cenſure of ſuch as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure other mens writings and arguments, not by the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the Scripture and Reaſon, but by opinions and practices grounded upon an implicit faith in their Teachers, from theſe I look for an out-cry like to that of <hi>Micha, Iudges</hi> 18.24. <hi>And he ſaid, ye have taken away my gods which I have made, and the Prieſt and ye are gone away, and what have I more? and what is this that ye ſay unto me, what aileth thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, that if I were conſiderable in that which they call Learning, I might gain the repute to raiſe a ſwarm of ſuch hornets about my eares, that if it were in their power would ſting me to death.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble thee further ar preſent, but leave thee to judge the inſuing Diſcourſe, as thou findeſt it moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Scripture and Reaſon, and ſo reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend, <hi>R. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:5"/>
            <head>To my loving and friendly Neighbours, the Pariſhioners of the Pariſh of S. <hi>Margarets</hi> New Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, <hi>R. P.</hi> wiſheth you the true knowledge of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel here, and eternall happineſſe hereafter.</head>
            <p>FRiends and Neighbours, having peruſed a piece, preſented to the Pariſhioners in generall, entituled, Caſes conſidered and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or Pills to purge Malignants, &amp;c. <hi>Calculated more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly</hi> (as Mr. Almanack-maker ſaith) <hi>for the Meridian of Margarets Fiſh-ſtreet hill,</hi> by a pretended Miniſter <hi>Tho. Brooks.</hi> And amongſt the rest, I having one of the hooks ſent unto me, reading it over, J thought it my duty to conſider; and if I might, to be reſolved of the caſe, from what ſpirit ſuch a language might flow; for as to my underſtanding, I do not remember that ever I read ſuch an Epistle through all the New Teſtament, either from the Apostles, or any other Miniſters; and by a Pamphlet to have the Pariſh posted in print through the Nation, and to be rendred under ſuch vile termes and foul aſperſions (by the malice of a Prieſt or pretended Minister) as might juſtly, were they true, make all ſober honeſt men refrain our company; yea and to deſtroy us in our trades and livelyhoods, by frighting people from dealing with ſo ungodly perſons as he pretends us to be: but for him to revile thoſe that he never ſpake word to, nor they to him; (and therefore not knowing what temper we are of) is ſuch a piece of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I am apt to think he either never read, or hath quite forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the nineth verſe of the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude;</hi> yet <hi>Michael</hi> the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, when he ſtrove against the divell, and diſputed about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt not bring against him a railing accuſation, but ſaid, the Lord rebuke thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:6"/>
            <head>Some Conſiderations on <hi>Mr. Brooks</hi> his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe beginning of his Epiſtle he makes an Apology for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by condemning many books, which he ſaith, <hi>ſhew the writers vanity, and vex the Readers patience;</hi> but what a worthy work his is, I hope will be made appear in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>He tells us alſo, that what he hath <hi>written, is out of faithfulneſſe to Chriſt, and love to ſouls.</hi> 'Tis like his zeal might be hot in writing it, being of generall concernment to the whole profeſſion; but had he not told us, of its being out of faithfulneſſe; <hi>he that is no Witch</hi> might eaſily have perceived it to be, not only out of faith, but alſo out of charity, but not out of ignorance on any termes.</p>
            <p>It is very true which he further ſpeaks in his Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>that thoſe that have the leaſt right to Ordinances, (and I may add Miniſtery) make the greatest noyſe and cry about them,</hi> ſo ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there are ſome ſuch pretended Miniſters in our times, that like empty veſſells make the greateſt ſound, who have onely a ſtudied form of fine words, and experience proves, are as affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately zealous in delivering them, as thoſe vagabond Jewes the ſons of <hi>Sceava</hi> were, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.13. <hi>We adjure you by Chriſt whom</hi> Paul <hi>preacheth;</hi> but read on the next verſe, and you will find they went not away without a reward fit for their work.</p>
            <p>He ſaith further, <hi>though his candle be but little, yet he muſt not hide it under a buſhell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly I hope the gentleman will let us have ſo much care of our ſelves, as not to follow an <hi>ignis fatnis,</hi> or ſuch a light (as is reported) that when men have followed it all night, they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the neerer their journeys end in the morning.</p>
            <p>And though he deſires, <hi>that the fruit might not be rejected for the trees ſake,</hi> I ſuppoſe it were well, could he demonſtrate unto us what manner of fruit he means; for if he means his book to be one of the fruits, ſome are apt to think ſuch fruit to be like the apples of <hi>Sodome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180294:6"/>
            <p>As for the reaſons he brings, they being conſidered, ſomething may be ſaid, but I deſire to be very briefe.</p>
            <p>And for the firſt, which is, <hi>that the honor, truth, and wayes of Chriſt, which are dearer to him then his life may be vindicated, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have read of ſome, who through blind zeal have offered great violence to their own bodies, as in the caſe of the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.28. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, though I give my body to be burned, and have not love, it profiteth me nothing.</p>
            <p>And for the gentlemans charity, you have it in the ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which I ſhall only name in ſhort, and leave both it, and thoſe Characters which he is pleaſed to beſtow on the Pariſhioners as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies to prove the truth of his Miniſtery by, which are, <hi>that the foul months of prophane, ignorant, malignant, and ſcandalous perſons may be effectually ſtope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the third, <hi>That the honeſt, just, and righteous proceedings of the honorable Committee may be manifeſted, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe it is a greater mercy then hath formerly been enjoyed by the people of this Nation, that thoſe in authority are tender of the conſciences of Chriſtians; but let me tell you, it is little or no thanks to the Prieſts; and farther I find, that when ever that Tribe hath been dandled on the knees of Authority, they have common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a requitall plotted, and many times effected the ruine of their Promoters, if they have not on all occaſions been ready to humor them in executing their malice againſt pretended Heretikes. I could largely inſtance in this, but deſire brevity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>that the importunate deſires of ſeverall Miniſters and Chriſtians might be ſatisfied, eſpecially thoſe to whom he preaches, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly if ſeverall Miniſters ſaw it before it was publiſhed, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der none was ſo kind as to put in <hi>Imprimatur</hi> to it, or to write an <hi>Encomium</hi> in Praiſe of the work, ſeeing they deſired ſo importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately to have it publiſhed, that we might have known the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but for thoſe other Chriſtians, to whom he faith he preaches, I ſhould rather judge it to be done by an implicit faith, then upon mature deliberation, to poſt it into the world. But I remember what Chriſt told the Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.15. that they compaſſed Sea and Land to make one of their profeſſion; and what got he, but to be twofold more the child of the divell then before.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>That his Miniſtery and good name, which ſhould be dearer to him then his life, may be vindicated, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180294:7"/>
            <p>Oh this ſweet morfell the Miniſtery! this great <hi>Dianah</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians!</hi> ſhould this become unmasked and undervalued, there might be a weeping, like that of the Merchants of <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 18. having none to buy their wares: But for his good name which he ſo highly prizes, and values at ſo dear a rate, certainly it had need be better then ordinary, when in exalting his own, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fames and vilifies the reputation and good names of all the men in the Pariſh, be pleaſed to conſider one text, becauſe I would not be tedious, it is <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. &amp; 5. <hi>Hipocrite first cast out the beam out of thine own eye, and then thou ſhalt ſee clearly to caſt out the mote out of thy brothers eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>that others may be undeceived, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I am fully perſwaded that his writing this laſt book will prove as effectuall for the undeceiving many people, as any thing that could have been propounded; for I believe moſt people that have read the book, did before account of him as a tender, humble, courteous, patient Saint, but I queſtion not, but by reading this they are clearly convinced of the contrary, and ſo undeceived. And whereas he ſaith, ſome ſaid there were eighteen, others twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix things charged againſt him, I ſuppoſe what they wanted of their number before, they may have now ſupplied with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh is of the ſame kind and temper with the ſecond, and therefore for brevity I paſſe it.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>becauſe his Caſe is a gener all Caſe, and reaches all the godly conſcientions Miuiſters in England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Truly I much commend the Captain for reſerving ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Party for the Rear-guard, and it is an old Proverb, <hi>that many hands make lightwork;</hi> but had he been confident of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which he pretends to, and believing in him, who he ſaith ſent him on the work, he need not make Proclamation to muſter up all the godly conſcientious Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> for fear of theirs and his being outed and routed by the prophane, ignorant, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party, as you may read <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 1.17, 18. <hi>Thou therefore truſſe up thy loynes, and ariſe and ſpeak unto them all that I command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, be not afraid of their faces, leſt I deſtroy thee before them, for I, behold I, have made thee a defenced City, and an iron Pillar, and walls of braſſe againſt the whole Land, againſt the Kings of</hi> Judah, <hi>and against the Princes thereof, againſt the Prieſts thereof, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180294:7"/>the people of the Land.</hi> And ſo was it in the caſe of <hi>Stephen, Paul,</hi> and others of the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt; but we find it was notable policy in <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-Smith to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a tottering worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.24, 25, 26. ver. to call together the craftſmen of like imployment; and it was a perſwaſive argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to tell them, Sirs you know by this craft we have our goods, &amp;c. as you may read at large, and make ſuch an application as is moſt reaſonable. I will not farther enlarge on this, leſt I ſhould ſeem tedious, but having paſt the door, I would willingly take a ſhort ſurvey of the houſe and furniture; ſo deſiring you as loving friends and neighbours to bear with my weakneſſe, conſidering I write not myſelf Clark, but Fiſhmonger; &amp; therefore you may allow me a few grains of a favourable conſtruction, more then to him that hath ſpent a large eſtate at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> to attain the art of eloquent writing and ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>Thus deſiring the Lord in mercy ſo to direct us, that we may clearly underſtand his will, reveal'd in his word and underſtanding, that he would enable us to practiſe in our lives, ſo as may make moſt for his glory, and our own comfort, both here and hereafter, is the prayer of your friend and neighbour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180294:8"/>
            <head>Obſervations on Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble.</head>
            <p>THe next thing that comes in courſe is the Preamble he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to make before the Honorable Committee, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And in it let us conſider firſt his intentions, and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the thing it ſelf, and ſee what they will reſolve us of.</p>
            <p>Firſt the intention of the ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Whither Alas doth the countenance of Authority and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, hurry perſons, who pretend moſt holineſſe, when once they forget themſelves, forſaking the fountain of living water, and digging to themſelves Ceſternes, broken Ceſternes that can hold no water?</p>
            <p>In the 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> from the 1. to the 18. we find Chriſt ſending out his Diſciples to preach the Goſpell, and tells them how they ought to behave themſelves, and what uſage they muſt expect from the world; for in the 18. <hi>ver.</hi> he tells them; they ſhall be brought before Governers and Kings for his ſake, &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>but when they deliver you up, take no thought how or what you ſhall ſay, for it ſhall be given you in that hour what you ſhall ſay, ver.</hi> 20. <hi>for it is not ye that ſpeak, but the ſpirit of your Father which ſpeaketh in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be an abſolute command of Chriſt to the Preachers of the Goſpel, not to ſtudy or premeditate what they ſhall ſay when they are brought before Rulers and Governers, for ſpeaking and practiſing what he commands them: Truly for my part I think the gentleman hath but little cauſe to brag of his intended ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Committee; I ſhall not be ſo cenforious, as to judge this intended and premeditated ſpeech a wilfull ſin againſt conſcience, but rather think it almoſt as great a weakneſſe of faith, as when <hi>Peter</hi> denied his Maſter.</p>
            <p>And I hope when he once conſiders his weakneſſe, in letting ſuch an Errata ſlip into the world, he will be ſo far from boaſting of it, that he will call it in, and publiſh his repentance in the room of it.</p>
            <p>The intended Preamble he begins with, <hi>it was a divine ſaying of</hi> Seneca, <hi>no man ſets a better rate upon vertue, then he that looſeth a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180294:8"/>good name to keep a good Conſcience.</hi> Ah <hi>Seneca!</hi> 'tis well the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man found you, for if he had not, he might have loſt the beginning of his Preamble, but as for the divinity in the ſentence, I wonder whether it be Church or School divinity, for we look for ſentences which are divine from Scripture, unleſſe a miracle to confirm them; but ſurely it is no miracle that his Criple ſhould walk, having two ſuch cruches as <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi> to ſupport it, but with an eye of pity take compaſſion on the gentleman, and conſider his caſe, which is very ſad, having ſuch ſhrewd juſtlings on both ſides, as may eaſily turn a weak ſtomack, ſeeing one ſort of people deny him to be a Scholar, others that he hath the qualiſications, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing charactets of a Miniſter of the Goſpel, the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I hope he hath ſufficiently confuted, by his Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, in his (Pills or) book, more eſpecially by the <hi>initiall letter</hi> (ט) <hi>of the Hebrew word</hi> Tob, <hi>that in the text is rendred good, is big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger shen ordinary, to ſhew the more then ordinary excellency of a good name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope this reaſon may ſilence all objections in that kind, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing produced <hi>ab origine.</hi> And for the other, he may, if he can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them when he comes to debate the buſineſſe in publique: But to come more cloſely to the buſineſſe, I remember what is ſaid <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. when <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell to ſpeak in defence and vindication of truth and themſelves, it was in this manner; then <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles anſwered and ſaid, <hi>we ought rather to obey God then men, &amp;c.</hi> And when <hi>Stephen</hi> anſwered for himſelf before the Councell, in that large and admitable ſpeech of his, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. he neither brought <hi>Seneca, Lactantius,</hi> or the like to ſpeak for him, or to help him out at a dead lift, but begins, <hi>Men, Brethren, and Fathers hearken, the God of glory appeared to our Father</hi> Abtaham, <hi>while he was in Meſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia, before he dwelt in Charan, &amp;c.</hi> but ſuch gentlemen as he is, ſure think they may ſpeak and do any thing without controul, and yet paſſe for true Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The former part of the Preamble I take as it is, <hi>his glorying in his good nnme, good conſcience, and holdneſſe therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the two former, if he hath them not, I wiſh he may, but as for the later, I ſuppoſe he is ſufficiently furniſhed withall, elſe his Pills had never been preſcribed.</p>
            <p>But concerning what he ſayes of (as he is pleaſed to ſtile them)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180294:9"/>
               <hi>the prophane, ignorant, maliguant, and ſeandalous Petitioners, as</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius <hi>ſaith of</hi> Lucian, <hi>he ſpared neither God nor man;</hi> me-thinks this his opinion of them is beyond the bounds of charity.</p>
            <p>But if they in requitall ſhould think of him; as it was the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> of <hi>Peter Aretine</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> which is thus engliſhed:</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Tuſcan <hi>Aretine</hi> lies herein grave,</l>
               <l>That againſt all, excepting God did rave;</l>
               <l>And if the reaſon you deſire to have,</l>
               <l>He knew him not, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the next place he ſaith, <hi>'tis ſaid of</hi> Cataline <hi>that he was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound and bundle of warring lusts and vices, ſuch are theſe Petitioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the compariſon, it is fool to the purpoſe, and ſo ſuteable to the perſons in all particulars, that I ſhall leave it with an <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> as one of his high raptures, or ſpiritual expreſſions.</p>
            <p>But the next ſentence is more admirable, wherein he compares the Petitioners <hi>to raging made tygers, when they ſmell the fragrancy of Spices, ſuen are they, ſaith he, when they ſmell the fragrancy of the graces of Gods Spirit, in the principles and practiſes, in the lives and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious exerciſes of the people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly it is a mercy, that as yet all the Petitioners that I hear of are in their right minds, but I confeſſe ſuch ſtrong purging pills as the Gentlemans are, is the ready way to make men inraged and mad: And this I ſuppoſe may be one of the principles and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the lives and religious exerciſes of the people he ſpeaks of, which if it be ſo, I am apt to believe he is not beſide the cuſhion; but if he means otherwiſe, I beſeech him that he would not judge, leaſt he be judged.</p>
            <p>In the next place he tells us (if we have faith enough to believe his bare word) <hi>that he hath preached the Goſpell above theſe thirteen years, and not only ſo, but that he hath many precious ſeals of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, which are his living Epistles, and walking Certificates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly the more holy, juſt, and good men are, and that they love vertue and goodneſſe for its own ſake (and not pretending Religion to attain preferment, and ſuch as may juſt ſuit with the temper of the times) I believe it ought to be a rejoycing to men &amp; Angells; but if converſion from prophaneneſſe, to an acknowled ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and profeſſion of faith, nay and to be zealous in a forme of worſhip, and blameleſſe in converſation, be an argument to prove a true Miniſtery, I ſuppoſe very many perſons under both
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180294:9"/>the forms of Epiſcopacy and Presbytery, were and are as holy and blameleſſe in their converſations, as any of thoſe that pretend to more pure di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>penſations: And for all that, few of our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have ſcarre ſo much charity as to judge them to be true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell; nay if the Gentlemans argument may be granted, I ſuppoſe the Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites might produce three for our one, and upon that account prove themſelves as true Miniſters as any in the world.</p>
            <p>In the next place he ſaith, <hi>in all his time none have ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo malicious, impudent, and ignorant, as to petition againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for their being ignorant in petitioning againſt him, it may be 'tis true, they not apprehending he could ſo effectually oppoſe them when it came to a hearing; but for the other termes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and impudence for petitioning is a doctrine contrary to the principles of all reaſon and liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; and if petitioning, which hath generally been concluded on, to be the moſt humble, innocent, and harmleſſe way of addreſſe, if that muſt be branded with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and malice, it were well if the gentleman had preſcribed ſomething in the room of it that might have been leſſe offenſive to his ſtomack; and if petitioning deſerve the brand of impudence, what titles would he have found for a proteſtation againſt him!</p>
            <p>But in concluſion, he is confident, <hi>that this act of the Petitioners ſhall make for his externall, internall, and eternall good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So am I as confident as himſelf; and firſt for his externall good, which I conclude to be his maintenance, I believe he is more fully confirmed in the benefice by their oopoſition, then he was before.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the <hi>internall good,</hi> he may be much more quieted in his mind, being delivered from the fear of any more ſuch oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, having cruſht the Petitioners ſo effectually.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for the <hi>eternall good,</hi> if he ſhould unfainedly repent, and deſire forgiveneſſe of the Petitioners, for thoſe black brands and foul aſperſions he hath caſt upon them, either by ignorance or malice, I queſtion not but they would freely forgive him.</p>
            <p>And for a cloſe to the Preamble, I ſhould adviſe the gentleman, if ever he ſhould meet with ſuch a ſort of people againe, who as he conceives, are ſuch oppoſers of the Miniſtery, not to follow the dictates of his own braine, how good ſoever they may ſeeme unto him, for as the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith 17. &amp; 9. <hi>the heart is deceitfull above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180294:10"/>But to follow the abſolute rule of Chriſt, if he be one of his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, which he gave to his Apoſtles in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. and 14. <hi>and whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor hear your words, when you depart out of that houſe or City, ſhake off the duſt off your feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truly I ſay unto you, it ſhall be eaſier for the Land of Sodom and Gomorrah, in the day of Judgement, then for that City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having done with the Preamble, the next thing in courſe is the Petition it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Which if this diſcourſe ſhould chance to come to the hands of ſtrangers, they may take a full view of it, and make the moſt ſtrict ſcrutiny into it, and ſee whether either it, or the Petitioners, are ſuch monſters as they are rendred.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To the Honorable Committee for Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred MINISTERS.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the Pariſhioners of <hi>Margaret New-Fiſhſtreet, London,</hi> whoſe names are hereunto ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</head>
                        <opener>Shewing,</opener>
                        <p>THat one Mr. <hi>Thomas Brooks,</hi> was by order of your Honors, dated the twenty third of <hi>March,</hi> 1651. appointed to preach for a moneth, next enſuing, as Probationer; to the end, that upon the Pariſhioners, and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> mutuall triall of each other, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> might continue, or your Petitioners have ſome other to officiate amongſt them.</p>
                        <p>Your Petitioners are humbly bold to offer to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors conſideration, that they have had triall of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> ever ſince your Honors Order, but cannot find that comfort to their ſouls they hoped; nor indeed is the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180294:10"/>ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> ſo qualified to your Petitioners underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as to remain any longer with them. And further, your Petitioners ſay, that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> refuſeth to afford your Petitioners the uſe of the Ordinances of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, nor will he bury their dead.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The Petitioners therefore humbly pray, that your Honors will be pleaſed to revoke your Order, and give liberty to your Petitioners for ſix moneths, to preſent a fit perſon to your Honors to be their Miniſter; and in the mean time, that Sequestrators may be appointed to provide for the ſervice of the Cure, out of ſuch money, as ſhall ariſe for tythes out of the ſaid Pariſh; And,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>IF you pleaſe ſeriouſly to conſider of the Petition, I believe you will not find one word of Malignancy or diſaffection to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, but meerly to entreat for that in point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which to their underſtandings ſeemeth moſt reaſonable; and if this be not agreeable to all thoſe principles and reaſons which have been ſtill preſſed for liberty of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> let the world judge. And I hope the gentleman will not force a practiſe, before he convinces the underſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:180294:11"/>
            <head>Obſervations on ſome of his Quaeries.</head>
            <p>IN the next place I come to the Quaeries he makes on the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants Petition,</hi> as he termes them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whereas he ſaith, <hi>it was never propounded to him to preach as Probationer amongst them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly how or upon what termes he came in I know not, neither did I trouble my ſelf about the choice, either for or againſt him, but I thought with my ſelf, and as ſome others ſaid, we had as good to have him as a worſe, ſeeing one we muſt have; neither knew I of the Petition, or ever ſee it, before he printed it; neither had I troubled my ſelf with him or his way, had he been quiet; but as I ſaid before, for him to render the Pariſh in generall under a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, but eſpecially the Petitioners, ſome of whom for divers years I have known, and truly may juſtly believe they are as honeſt, juſt, and righteous as himſelf, I am ſure more then ſome of his <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> I could ſay more, but will not, leaſt I might be accounted a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atterer.</p>
            <p>But truly it may be the Petitioners, as well as my ſelfe, care not to ſpend our time to hear; <hi>this is a brave word, this a fine word, this is a ſweet word;</hi> and to have him ſpeak with reverence, that had not Chriſt accompliſhed the work of Redemption, for which he was ſent, that God would have made heaven too hot to hold him, and the like, but conſidering the whole Pariſh to lie under a reproach, although I being one of the meaneſt, yet thought it my duty, (though but weakly) to take off the ſtain ſo much as I might, for the Proverb is tread on a worm, and it will turn: And leaſt our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence might conclude us to be altogether ſuch as the gentleman himſelf, and friends, who preſt him to publiſh the book are: plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to terme us, there could not in reaſon have been leſſe ſaid.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>he preached above twenty Sermons in the winter on the Lecture nights:</hi> But I wiſh he had told us what he meaneth by preaching, becauſe I judge the Goſpell preaching is to ſpeak as the Spirit gives utterance, and not the reading of a few written Notes,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180294:11"/>that have been premeditated and ſtudied five or ſix dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And alſo I further deſire to know what rule or example there is in the Goſpell, that ever any Miniſter of the Goſpel did, or ought to preach upon triall to gain a benefice.</p>
            <p>In the fourth Quaery he ſaith, <hi>the prophane, malignant Petitioners had neither a hand in chuſing, nor hearts to make triall of his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that they may well have a black brand put upon them, as men void of common honeſty and ingenuity, &amp;c.</hi> with more of the ſame language, which I ſuppoſe he hath done to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which, I ſay, if it ſhould be granted that they had neither a hand in chuſing, nor hearts to make triall of his Miniſtery, yet I ſuppoſe the gentleman had a triall of their money, and alſo a heart to make uſe of it, though by his owne words they had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it, and therefore in modeſty might have uſed them more kindly: And whereas he ſaith, that what the Petitioners ſpeak in the Petition, is as far from truth, as the Petitioners are from being reall friends to the preſent Authority of the Nation; it is clear that the Petitioners do own the preſent Authority, by their humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe to the Honorable Committee for Plundred Miniſters.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to what he ſays, I beſeech you bear with a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. What ſhall I ſay to the gentleman? ſhall I retort his own language upon him, as one being void of common honeſty &amp; inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity? for had the Petitioners formerly been malignant, &amp; enemies the preſent Government, yet conſidering the preſent Authority, have been graciouſly pleaſed to paſſe a generall Act of Pardon and Oblivion, whereby all that emulation and heart-burning betweene ſeverall parties, might be a greed and quite forgotten, for him to rake up the embers, and blow the coals of diviſion afreſh in that kind, by branding of them with that which ought not once to be mentioned, argues but little in the gentleman, either of ingenuity or honeſty.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing that he is of ſuch a ſtrain, that he cares not what it be, ſo he can find any thing to render the perſons odious, with whom he is offended, I ſhall take the boldneſſe to remember him of ſome paſſages that may be very conſiderable, as to the thing in hand.</p>
            <p>How his affections might be to the preſent Government in the late Kings time, I know not; but I did then, and ſtill do know di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180294:12"/>perſons which are moſt zealous for a Congregationall way; that were the greateſt promoters of his intereſt of any people I knew in the City, and ſuch as were not ordinary members, but Preachers ſo called; I could name the perſons, time, and places, but ſhall only give a hint of ſomething that I ſpeak upon my owne knowledge, that you may know, and take notice how little the preſent Authority are beholding to ſome Churchmen, though ſince I ſee the ſame perſons are exceedingly countenanced and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</p>
            <p>About the time the late King was brought to <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, theſe Churchmen had a Petition on foot to preſſe on a Perſonall Treaty, they uſed all the prevailing arguments that might be to get hands to it, and perſons to own it. Amongſt the reſt, ſayes a Preacher, I ſee no ſafety, nor how the breach can be made up without compliance with the King. And ſaid moreover, that he had an oportunity to ſpeak to him, and that he thought there was much of God in him, and that he would be willing to comply to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, both religious and civill, and abundance more that was very high in the commendation of him; as in particular, that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to grant the <hi>Militia</hi> for ſo many years, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anſwer was made, that he had no <hi>Militia</hi> left to grant, for if it had been his before, yet the right was onely by the power of the Sword, and by the ſame power he had loſt it; but if he had a right to grant a term of years, that then the power muſt reſt in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which was a doctrine contrary to all the Declarations of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in that caſe.</p>
            <p>He ſaid moreover, that he would grant Liberty of Conſcience, as much as could be deſired with an Act of Oblivion, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which are too long to inſert.</p>
            <p>But anſwer was made, he was not in a capacity to grant, for he was no better then a priſoner, and that he had oppoſed ſo long as he had any power left; and for him to grant an Act of Oblivion, was for to lay all the guilt and bloud of the Nations on them that oppoſed his proceedings, and how diſhonorable it would be to ask forgiveneſſe of a conquered enemy, let the world judge: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a large debate, ſayes the Gentleman, I profeſſe, I thought not that what I propound might not be for a publike good, I would never perſwade to it: I had never inſtanced this, but that the vail might be taken off from ſome Churchmens faces, that the world
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180294:12"/>might not ſuppoſe they were the onely Promoters of the preſent Authority, when indeed the fault of the Perſonall Treaty, under which divers others ſuffered, they were the moſt guilty of, in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and perſwading to it, of any that ever I ſpake with.</p>
            <p>But amongſt all their pretendings to the annoynting of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and to make known the mind and will of God, that there ſhould not be one found amongſt them that could read the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing as it was done by <hi>Daniel,</hi> when he told the K. <hi>Belſhazzar, this is the interpretation of the thing, Dan.</hi> 5.6. <hi>God hath numbred thy Kingdome, and finiſhed it, thou art weighted in the balance, and found too light, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But truly I could not find any of our Churchmen, who pretend ſo much to know the mind of God, but were as ignorant of what God by his providence was about to do in overthrowing the late King, and renting the Kingdome from him, as any the Magitians, Aſtrologians, and Southſayers were to interpret the handwriting to the King of <hi>Babilon</hi> And as far from truth, and the mind of God were they in proſecuting the perſonall Treaty, as thoſe Prophets that counſell'd <hi>Ahab</hi> to go up to <hi>Ramoth Giliad</hi> and proſper.</p>
            <p>Friends, I deſire you would not look on me as an enemy to the wayes of Chriſt, and Goſpell obedience; for I know divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are eminent for a holy, juſt, and righteous converſation, unto whom I ſtand greatly engaged upon the higheſt account of friendſhip, that at this time, and I believe according to their light, do in ſincerity of heart walk in Church-fellowſhip: And divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my acquaintance, who upon good grounds have forſaken thoſe wayes, though in the higheſt formes, and yet retain the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of a holy life to wards God, and juſt dealings towards men; and therefore why ſhould we be ready to judge thoſe that are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above us, or below us in the practiſe of religious duties, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle concluded, that there was as well milk for babes in Chriſt, as meat for ſtrong men.</p>
            <p>But to return to the thing in hand, in the next place he ſayes, <hi>the Petitioners uſe to hear ſuch, whoſe malignant principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes are ſuch as their own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly whoever they hear, I believe they may ſoon hear as true Miniſters as himſelf: but it is no wonder to hear thoſe that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt to be offended and angry with thoſe that conform not to their way, though the ſame perſons, whileſt kept under, were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180294:13"/>the greateſt writers and pleaders for Liberty of Conſcience in the largeſt extent of any people in the Nation, but as the Proverb is, the Prieſt forgets that he was Clark; ſo when ſome have attained to what liberty themſelves deſire, they are preſently ready to tye up all others to their own humours, as I might largely inſtance.</p>
            <p>He tells us farther, <hi>that they ſay, they cannot find that comfort to their ſouls they hoped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly this ſeemes to me that they would gladly hear a Goſpell Miniſter, by whoſe preaching and practiſe they might receive both profit and comfort; and certainly there cannot be a ſurer ſign of their deſire to have it, then their being ſenſible of the want of it. But alas Chriſt tells the people, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16. that they muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to gather grapes of thornes, or figs of thiſtles.</p>
            <p>In the next place he is pleaſed to Quaerie, and runs a large cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference with inkhorn terms, the ſubſtance whereof is to prove, <hi>that the Petitioners have no right to Goſpel comforts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For a brief anſwer to which in generall, I ſay, if the largeſt and moſt gracious tenders of the free mercy of God for forgiveneſſe of ſin, and eternall ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt, be not to be offered to the vileſt of ſinners, I muſt unlearn divers Scriptures, which I do believe expreſly prove, that not only the mercy of God is ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and the ſatisfaction of Chriſt ſo undeniably full and ſufficient for the forgiveneſſe of ſins and eternall ſalvation by him for all perſons, that it is to be tendred to all without exceptions, unleſſe ſuch only who are ſo holy, that they think they need it not, for Chriſt himſelf ſpeaks in the like caſe, <hi>the whole have no need of the Phyſitian, and that he came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi> yet ſtill the proud Phariſees laid this to his charge, that he was a company keeper with, &amp; a friend to Publicans and ſinners. I ſpeak not this to juſtifie any perſon in a wicked way; but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the infinite love and mercy of God be not the way to bring in ignorant, prophane and ſcandalous perſons to obedience and conformity to the wayes of Chriſt, I would gladly learn, what is meant by the Commiſſion Chriſt gave to his Apoſtles, <hi>Mark</hi> ult. and 15. and he ſaid unto them, <hi>go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpell to every creature, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Goſpel be the declaration of glad tidings of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that it muſt be preached to every creature, by the expreſſe command and Commiſſion of Chriſt himſelf, I wonder how any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180294:13"/>dare be ſuch Traytors to the Lord Jeſus, if he hath appointed them to preach the Goſpell, as to conceal the glad tiding of the Goſpel of grace and mercy, and to thunder out the curſes and thre atnings of the Law in the room of it, againſt them, who they call ignorant and prophane ſinners.</p>
            <p>We find upon the birth of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.10. the Angell, who was the meſſenger to declare Chriſts coming into the world, what ſaid he but this? <hi>Be not afraid, for behold I bring you glad tidings of great joy that ſhall be to all people, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 13. when the heavenly ſouldiers ſung a Halelujah to the higheſt, was it any thing but glory <hi>to God on high, peace on earth, and good will towards men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, the conſideration of the Goſpell, as it is made knowne in the Scriptures, is a thing ſo large, admirable and excellent, that in this difcourſe I have neither time nor oportunity to treat of it, and befides ſome famous men have excellently, and are at preſent writing on that ſubject.</p>
            <p>I ſhould have made bold to have unravelled the Quaeries, piece by piece, and have ſeen how agreeable they are in all particulars to the mind of Chriſt in the Goſpell: But I have given you this but as a taſt of what I intend, if ever it pleaſe God I ſhall ſpeak to it again; yet in this ſmall glaſſe I hope the gentleman may ſee, of how far different and ſtrange a countenance he is of from a true Miniſter of the Goſpel, by the matter contained in his late book, and alſo I deſire an anſwer to this Quaery.</p>
            <p>Whether the tender of the mercy of God in Chriſt Jeſus, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, faith, and ſalvation, be to be made to them in a Church-fellowſhip, or thoſe without?</p>
            <p>That I may be brief, I deſire you ſeriouſly to conſider one Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, becauſe the gent leman pretends to ſo many heavenly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, gifts of the Spirit, and the bird in the boſome, that makes a heaven of joy in his heart, for 'tis poſſible he may be deceived as much, if not more then that people which God ownes to be a true Church; and it is that which God himſelfe ſpeaks to the Church of <hi>Laodicea, Rev.</hi> 5.17. <hi>For thou ſayeſt I am rich, and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing, and knoweſt not how thou art wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think he may upon ferious conſiderations of his Miniſtery, ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did, 39, 37. <hi>I will lay my hand upon my mouth, once have I ſpoken but will anſwer no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:180294:14"/>
            <p>In the next place the gentleman tells us of his qualifications, and becauſe he ſaith further, <hi>that the underſtandings of ignorant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and ſecandalous perſons, are not a fit rule or ſtandard to try the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities or qualifications of ſuch Miniſters as are not Miniſters of the letter, but of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Quaeries propounded to be debated in Publique.</head>
               <p>FOr the triall of his gifts and qualifications, I here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, that which I hope is equall, juſt, and reaſonable, that we may in a friendly, loving, and free manner, make an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the Scriptures, and ſee what they hold forth to be the characters and qualifications of a true Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and to that end, that he would ſave a labour of writing, and charge of printing, and give the Pariſhioers, and ſome other friends, a publike meeting, once a week in the Pariſh Church, where freedome of ſpeech may be to all that deſire it, they ſpeaking to the Queſtion, and one at a time, and to ſpend two hours in an evening in the inquiry of the characters and qualifications of a Miniſter of the Spirit; and in this I hope he will grant the Scripture to be a right rule, and equall ſtandard.</p>
               <p>In order whereunto, I ſhall inſert a few Quaeries as fit matter to be inquired into.</p>
               <p>In the 4. of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> 8.11, 12. we find what Miniſters Chriſt gave to the Church at his Aſcenſion; in theſe words, <hi>and when he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up on high, he led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men, and he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Scripture we find two things chiefly contained, Firſt, what Miniſters Chriſt gave, Secondly, what end he gave them for.</p>
               <p>Now we may find in Scripture the ſeverall qualifications that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to every one of theſe Officers, and diſtinguiſhing characters to know thew one from another,</p>
               <p>And that it is ſo, I ſhall ſet downe the diſtinguiſhing characters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180294:14"/>which the Scriptures afford us to know an Apoſtle by. And leave the Gentleman, becauſe he ſaith he is a Miniſter of the Spirit, to give the like of the others according to the Scripture, that we may know under which of thoſe Qualifications and diſtinguiſhing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters he comes; for a Paſtor is not an Evangeliſt, nor an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt a Prophet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The firſt diſtinguiſhing Character that we finde of an Apoſtle in Scripture is, that he is a choſen witneſſe of the Reſurrection, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.22. 3.15. 4.33. 10.39.41. <hi>Luk</hi> 24.48.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An Apoſtle is one ſent forth to preach the Goſpel to all the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.14. to the end.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The office of an Apoſtle did comprehend in it all the other offices of the Miniſtery, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2.3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. An Apoſtle was one endued with all the gifts of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.9.</p>
               <p n="5">5. An Apoſtle was able to communicate theſe gifts by the laying on of their hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.6, 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Querie, Whether the office of Apoſtles was to ceaſe in the perſons of thoſe to whom the Commiſſion was at firſt given?</p>
               <p>And to this end I pray conſider, how long the Promiſe laſted, which is, <hi>Lo, I am with you alway untill the end of the world.</hi> Chriſt could not be with their Perſons, for we finde in Scripture, that moſt of them were martyred in a few yeares after his Aſcenſion; and yet the Commiſſion of an Apoſtle was to <hi>teach and baptize all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, teaching them to abſerve all things whatſoever Chriſt had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them.</hi> And in the 4. of the Epheſians, we finde that upon the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, they were the firſt and chiefe Officers of the Church, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. that were given for the perfecting of the Saints, for the worke of the Miniſtry, for the Edifying the body of Chriſt: <hi>till all come in the unitie of faith and the knowledge of the Sonne of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Stature of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> I will not enlarge farther at preſent expecting to have it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated at large in Publick.</p>
               <p>And becauſe he pretends much of having a commiſſion to preach and Baptiſe,</p>
               <p n="3">3. I Querie who appoynted him to preach or gave him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Baptiſe.</p>
               <p>Which two things I expect to have ſubſtantially proved by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:180294:15"/>
               <p n="4">4. Querie, Where we finde any in Scripture that did Baptize with water after Chriſts Aſcenſion, that did not alſo Baptize with the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2, 3, 4.5. <hi>And he ſaid unto them, have ye received the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye beleeved? and they ſaid unto him, we have not ſo much as heard, whether there be any Holy Ghoſt, and he ſaid unto them, unto what then were ye Baptized? and they ſaid, unto Johns Baptiſme, &amp;c.</hi> And in verſe 6. <hi>And when Paul had laid his hands upon them, the Holy Ghoſt came on them, and they ſpake with tongues and Propheſied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Querie, Whether the Baptiſme with water after Chriſts Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion was the Baptiſme of Chriſt, or a contiouation of <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme? And conſider theſe Scriptures, and divers others of the ſame kinde, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 3.8. <hi>I indeede Baptize you with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but he ſhall Baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Act. 11.15, 16. <hi>And as I began to speake, the holy Ghoſt fell on them, as on us at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Then remembred I the word of the Lord how that he ſaid John in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Baptized with water, but ye ſhal be Baptized with the holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Querie, What the Scriptures doe hold forth the Baptiſme of the Spirit to be, after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>We finde the Diſciples of Chriſt furniſhed with very great gifts while he was with them, yet ſtill he ſixt their thoughts upon what they ſhould expect to receive after his departure from them, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.39. <hi>But this he ſpake of the spirit, which they that beleeve on him ſhould receive, for the Holy Ghoſt was not yet given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Querie, What command the Gentleman hath in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Biptize Infants?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether Infants can poſſibly be capable of the Baptiſme of the Spirit, having neither knowledge, faith, nor repentance?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether in Scripture we reade of any that did Baptize with water after Chriſts Aſcenſion, whoſe Preaching and Doctrine was not confirmed by fignes and miracles?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whether the Scripture holds forth that all the gifts of the Spirit were in particular Churches, after the Aſcenſion? And theſe I hope will be a ſufficient ground work, for the beginning of ſuch an inquiry, as through Gods bleſſing thereon, may much enlighten our underſtandings in the order, method, and practice of Goſpell obedience.</p>
               <p>I ſhall make bold to add two Queries more, which are of an other nature, which I would willingly know.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:180294:15"/>
               <p n="1">1. Whether it be not <hi>jure Divino,</hi> and agreeable to the practice of the Primitive Preachers, for men nowadayes to receive money for Preaching, from ſuch as never intend to heare them?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether it be not more reaſonable for me, to ſend the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman an Anſwer to his booke, then for him to ſend me a Paper of his Pills, at adventure, not knowing the conſtitution of my body, and having never ſpake word to me in his life?</p>
               <p>But to haſten to a Concluſion, becauſe I am ſtraitned in time, and have not a conveniency to anſwer to every particular which he calls Reaſons, eſpecially that Prophane perſons ought not to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into a Church Society. And inſtances in the caſe of <hi>Judas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the underſtanding whereof, I deſire to know whether Chriſt and his Diſciples were a Church before the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament of the Supper? <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. if they were, then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <hi>Judas</hi> was a Member, though a wicked one.</p>
               <p>But for that lamentable Lame thing which he calls his fourth Reaſon, which is this: <hi>That Chriſt acted in giving the Sacrament, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially as he was man, leaving them a Pattern to walke by that ſhould come after him, and ſuch was the carriage of Chriſt towards</hi> Judas <hi>all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</hi> Now from his own words, if this be the Patterne that Chriſt left to his ſucceeding Miniſtery, (whereof he pretends himſelfe to be one,) I Querie who granted him a diſpenſation not to follow it?</p>
               <p>And for that bold affirmation of his in the following words, <hi>that Chriſt did not act towards Judas, as he was an all-ſeeing God, or the heart maker or heart ſearcher,</hi> &amp;c. Truly I ſuppoſe he would have the Reader to take that upon truſt, or it may be it is one of his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, for he brings not the leaſt tittle of Scripture to prove it by. But I wonder what he thinkes of <hi>Peters</hi> acting in the caſe of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Act</hi> 5. whether he acted in the Miniſteriall office as God or man, when all will grant, that Chriſt was Maſter, and <hi>Peter</hi> but Servant?</p>
               <p>But that point of the lawfulneſſe of refuſing prophane Perſons, who deſire to joyne themſelves to a Congregation, would aske a large debate; and though I might draw divers Arguments from this caſe of <hi>Judas.</hi> I ſhall offer one inſtance more Materiall, which is, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.13. where we finde <hi>Simon Magus</hi> though a Witch, yet was he admitted into the Church by being baptized. Though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>Peter</hi> told him, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>That he was in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:180294:16"/>
               <p>Truly I gladly haſten to a Concluſion, and I hope by this little I ſay, you will eaſily judge what manner of Mettle the reſt of the Gentlemans Diſcouſe is made up of. And though he may tell us of his leaving the Spirit, yet I ſuppoſe he was not guided by the Spirit in the penning his laſt booke (unleſſe it were a Spirit of delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) for the Spirit which Chriſt promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. <hi>Howbeit when he is come which is the Spirit of truth, he will leade you into all truth.</hi> But to my underſtanding, I never read vanity, in ſo large a Character and ſmall a volume, as in the booke intituled, <hi>Pills to purge Malignants,</hi> conſidering to what end he ſaith it was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Well, let us rather pitty then provoke the Gentleman, by diſcovering any more of his weakneſſe, at preſent remembring this charitable Motto: <hi>Humanum eſt errare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having briefly, gently, and ſeriouſly (as I may) handled the Gentlemans diſcourſe, I hope he will as a loving Neighbour, kindly accept it, when he findes that he hath ſome Neighbours, that are willing, ſo farre as abilities will give them leave, to requite his Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies.</p>
               <p>And for a Concluſion, I deſire that ſome paſſages in Scripture, which are of wonderfull worth and weight may be humbly, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and ingeniouſly conſidered, which may tend both to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and comfort of thoſe that deſire truly to feare God, and walke in his wayes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>We finde in Scripture that there are two fearfull ſinnes that moſt people have beene guilty of; The one in being Stubborne and Rebellious againſt the Will and Councell of God, declared by his Meſſengers and Miniſters: The other delight in believing and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in Lying Vanites, <hi>viz.</hi> the Dreames and Divinations of mens hearts whom God never ſent. And to the end we may not fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der either of theſe extreames; it is our duty to take a ſurvey of both theſe particulars, and to inquire by that perfect rule of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſo farre as we are able to underſtand, and try, who are true, and who are falſe Miniſters and Meſſengers. That ſo as on the one hand we may not be found Fighters againſt God, or Contemners of his Miniſters; ſo on the other, we might not by blinde obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, be ſo led by blinde guides, that at laſt both we and they fall into the ditch.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe, we finde the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180294:16"/>guilty of, both before, in, and after the Captivity. You cannot be ignorant of divers examples in that kinde.</p>
            <p>Jer. 7.13, 14, 15. <hi>Therefore now becauſe ye have done all theſe workes,</hi> ſaith the Lord. <hi>and I roſe up early and spake unto you, but when I spake you would not heare me, neither when I called would you anſwer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And I will caſt you out of my ſight, as I have caſt out all your brethren, even the whole ſeede of Ephraim,</hi> verſe 26. Chap. 7.8. Chap. 17.23.44.16. <hi>As for the word that thou haſt spoken unto us, in the name of the Lord we will not hearken unto thee, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo all the other Prophets declare the peoples Obſtinacy, Contempt, and Rebellion to the Commandements of God declared by his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. But afterwards, more eſpecially in abuſing thoſe gracious tenders of mercy unto eternall ſalvation by Chriſt himſelfe, and his Miniſters, as is teſtified <hi>John</hi> 1.11. <hi>He came unto his owne, and his owne received him not.</hi> And upon the firſt ſending out of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Goe not into the way of the Gentiles, and into any of the Cities of the Samaritans enter ye not.</hi> 6. <hi>But goe rather to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Yet for all this mercy and loving kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt Jeſus, we finde their Obſtinacy and Rebllion come to a heighth of Blaſphemy, when contrary to their owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they told Chriſt that he caſt out Devils by <hi>Belzehub:</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely a People come to ſuch a fulneſſe of iniquity, cannot be farre from that deſtruction, ſpoken of <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1.24. to the 31. <hi>Becauſe I have called and ye refuſed, I have stretched out my hand and none would regard but have deſpiſed all my Councell, and would none of my correction; I will alſo laugh at your deſtruction, and mock when your feare commeth like ſudden deſolation: and your destruction ſhall come like a whirle-winde, when affliction and anguiſh ſhall come upon you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I might much enlarge this, but deſire Brevity, that the diſcourſe may not <hi>ſhew the Writers Vanity, or vex the Readers Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as to the ſecond thing which is the peoples truſting in lies and vanities, even to their owne confuſion. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.19.</p>
            <p>We ſhall finde if we ſerioufly examine whence it ſprings, that the roote of all the miſchiefes, miſery, and deſtruction of Nations, is from their wicked Prieſts, lying Prophets, and pretended Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Miniſters of God, whom he never ſent, nor gave any Commiſſion unto. How ſad was the caſe of <hi>Ahab, Kings.</hi> 22. to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180294:17"/>have the advice and be thruſt forward by the councell of foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred lying Prophets to his owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>We finde when the Lord ſent <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to declare his wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the people of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. he mildly reaſons with the people, ſaying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I remember thee with the kindneſſe of thy youth, and the love of thy marriage, when thou wentest after me in the wilderneſſe in a land that was not ſowne:</hi> Verſe 3. <hi>Iſrael was a thing hallowed unto the Lord:</hi> Verſe 5. <hi>What iniquity have your Fathers found in me, that they are gone farre from me, and have walked after vanity, and are become vaine?</hi> But in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. we have the reaſon fully; <hi>The Prieſts ſaid not, where is the Lord? And they that ſhould miniſter the Law knew me not, the Paſtors alſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt me, and the Prophets prophecied in</hi> Baal, <hi>and went after things that did not profit.</hi> And chap. 4.30, 31. <hi>An horrible and filthy thing is committed in the Land, &amp;c.</hi> Chap. 14.14. <hi>The Prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie lies in my name, I have not ſent them, neither did I command them, neither spake I unto them, but they prophecie unto you a falſe viſion, and divination, and vanity, and deceitfulneſſe of their owne heart.</hi> Chapter 18.15. <hi>Becauſe my people have forgotten me, and have burnt Incenſe to vanity, and their Prophets have cauſed them to ſtumble in their wayes, from the ancient wayes; to walke in paths and way that is not trodden.</hi> Chapter 23.1.21. <hi>I have not ſent theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken unto them, yet they prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might bring a cloud of witneſſes to confirme what hath beene aſſerted, but you may read them at large.</p>
            <p>But let us inquire whether they gave the people any better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in the time that Chriſt and his Diſciples preached amongſt them. Truly all along the New Teſtament we finde them oppoſing the Doctrine, and perſecuting Chriſt and his Diſciples in perſon; and that they might be ſure to fill up the meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and to bring the Bloud of Chriſt and all the Prophets, upon their own heads, and unavoydable ruine on the Nation, you may read their councell at large, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.1. <hi>When the morning was come, all the chiefe Prieſts and Elders of the people, tooke councell againſt Jeſus to put him to death,</hi> and in the 20. you may ſee the influence they had upon the people: <hi>But the chiefe Prieſts and Elders perſwaded the multitude that they ſhould aske</hi> Barrabas <hi>and deſtroy</hi> Jeſus: But their wages was as ſad as their worke, when there was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180294:17"/>not one ſtone left ſtanding upon another in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that was not throwne downe. But were not theſe people a zealous, ſtrict, and exact people in their Religion, and wayes of Worſhip? Yea, and we finde Chriſt often ſpeaking of it, but withall diſcovering the worme at the roote, as their making of long prayers, when they meant to devoure widows houſes? And their tything of herbs, when they neglected Judgement and Righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. Did they not condemne Chriſt for keeping company with the Publicans and ſinners, and yet did not they drive a trade of treaſon by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale with <hi>Judas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thinke you they were not like to teach the people truth well, when they had a Mint of Lyes going to furniſh the <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers with? when they hired them to ſay, <hi>his Diſciples came by night and ſtole him away while we ſlept?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were they not a people that boaſted much in their Church and Ordinances, <hi>John</hi> 8.33. <hi>Of being Abrahams children and free,</hi> and yet at that time they would, and afterwards did murder the Lord of life and glory? Was it not common for them to faſt (it may be twice a weeke) but was not the end to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe? And hath here not lately been Conſpiracy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion (againſt the preſent Government) rapt in the mantle of private Faſts, which the hand of Juſtice hath found out, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly puniſhed for all the Cloaks of preciſeſt Religion? If that Tribes ſufferings in this Nation hath not beene great, it is the better for them, if they make a right uſe of it; and leave them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their owne conditions, for theſe laſt 12. yeares. But I will give you a few examples of former times, and if to them they doe not, yet to me they ſtrike Horror and amazement, to conſider the dreadfull dealing of God, towards ſuch as have pretended to be his Meſſengers, when indeede they have beene abſolute Lyars, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning greedily after the errour of <hi>Balaam,</hi> to Prophecy for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and may well expect the reward of <hi>Corah.</hi> And that you may be ſure to know ſuch deceivers, they have ſo large a Character, that he that runs may reade it, <hi>Jude</hi> 19. theſe be they that ſeperate themſelves, having not the Spirit. We finde in the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. foure hundred and fifty of <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets, that after they had cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bawled all day, and cut themſelves with Knives and Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, could not prevaile any thing, to perſwade the people in the preſence of the true Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> what a tragicall hand did the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180294:18"/>poore deluding wretches make at the Brooke <hi>Kiſhon. Jeremiah</hi> 28.15, 16.17. <hi>Then ſaid the Prophet Jeremiah, unto the Prophet Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah, the Lord hath not ſent thee, but thou makeſt this people to truſt in a lye, therefore thus ſaith the Lord, behold I will caſt thee from of the face of the earth; this yeare thou ſhalt dye becauſe thou haſt taught Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Hananiah</hi> the Prophet dyed the ſame yeare in the ſeventh month. I will amongſt many, give you but one inſtance more, becauſe I haſten, <hi>Jer.</hi> 19.21, 22. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts and God of Iſrael, of Ahab the Sonne of Kolaiah, and Zedekiah, the Sonne of Maaſejah, which propheſie a lye unto you in my name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I will deliver them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon, and he ſhall ſlay them before your eyes: And of them ſhall be taken up a Curſe by all the Captivity of Judah, which are in Babylon, ſaying, the Lord make thee like Zedekiah, and like Ahab, whom the King of Babilon roasted in the fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly the Doctrine and uſe of theſe examples are ſo plaine, and eaſie to be underſtood in the Text, that I ſhall forbeare any large applications, but come to the thing, and that in ſhort. It hath beene the miſery of the world in generall, to pin their faith on their teachers ſleeves. And without Controverſie, if the Leaders of the People cauſe them to erre, they that are led by them, will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. How many hundred thouſands periſhed in dauncing after the pipe of <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Monke</hi> by his pretended revelation? perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading almoſt all Chriſtendome, to fight for the recovery of the holy Land from the Turkes, when the Scripture ſaith expreſly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.24. <hi>That the Jews ſhould be led away Captive into all Nations, and Hieruſalem ſhould be troden down of the Gentiles, untill the time of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay what brawlings, quarrellings and fightings is there in any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but to be ſure the Clergy ſo called, are promoters of it. (I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what comfort the Epiſcopall and Presbyterian Clergy have in their former abetting their Intereſt) and aſſuredly what ever at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is uppermoſt, if it be not of God it will fall. With what fury do both Popiſh &amp; Proteſtant Church-men excite poor ſouls to murder one the other, upon a Religious account, the one becauſe Idolaters, the other becauſe Hereticks. Nay, none ſo eager as they which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend moſt holineſſe, thundering out curſes of the largeſt ſize, upon the refuſers, as they pretend, of Chriſt and the Goſpell, when indeed it is onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>pe the power which keeps them under, whereby they may get into the Chaire to Lord it, as did the late Presbiters &amp; others, in the ruine of their Fathers the Biſhops, but no more of this at preſent.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:180294:18"/>
            <p>Now to the thing which is of moſt concernment, how ſhall we do to know who are true Miniſters, and if it be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſible to walk in a Goſpel obedience; for anſwer whereunto, in ſhort, I cannot find in Scripture that ever God appointed any to declare his will unto any perſon or people, but that they had ſomething more then their bare words to teſtifie their ſending as it was in the caſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> of the man of God that come from <hi>Iudah,</hi> and prophecied againſt the Altar in <hi>Bethel,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings cha.</hi> 13. of <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and ſo through the Old Teſtament; and in the New Teſtament Chriſt himſelf ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 5.31. <hi>if I ſhould bear witneſſe of my ſelfe, my witneſſe were not true,</hi> and ver. 36. <hi>but I have greater witneſſe then that of</hi> John, <hi>for the works which the Father have given me to finiſh, the ſame works that I do bear witneſſe of me, that the Father hath ſent me:</hi> Without queſtion the Scribes and Phariſees had a formall way of praying and teaching, but when Chriſt taught, he taught as one having authority, and not like unto them; and he tells thoſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8, 9. <hi>This people draweth neer unto me with their mouth, and honoreth me with their lips, but their heart is far off from me, but in vain they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the traditions of men.</hi> Joh. 9.1, 2. <hi>then called he his twelve Diſciples together, and gave them pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority over all divels, and to heal diſeaſes, and he ſent them forth to preach the Goſpel, and to cure the ſick,</hi> Mat. 10.7, 8. <hi>And as you go preach ſaying, the Kingdome of heaven is at hand, heal the ſick, cleanſe the Lepers, raiſe up the dead, caſt out the divels, freely ye have received, freely give,</hi> and this not to Apoſtles only, but promiſed to believers in generall, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17. And in the 20. we find the word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by miracles: Now if this was the confirmat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Miniſtery, I wonder our Miniſters are not endued with ſuch gifts, or prove to us from Scripture, that the Church and Miniſtery was to continue, and yet the gifts to ceaſe. But it may be objected that theſe gifts were given for bringing in of unbelievers, it were well if all in the Nation were believers, but certainly we had need have ſomething to ground our faith and obedience upon, more then bare words, ſeeing if you hear four preachers upon one text, it is much if three be not of a different opinion. But then comes in the great objection, what if we have not a true Miniſtery nor Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then we have no faith? well, not too haſty, it was a ſerious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> had with Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. about worſhip, and ver. 21. Jeſus ſaid unto her, woman believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, not at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180294:19"/>worſhip the Father, &amp;c. and ver. 24. God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth.</p>
            <p>Certainly where much is given, much is required, and ſo on the contrary; but if by reaſon of the overſpreading of abomination God hath withdrawn thoſe viſible gifts from the Miniſtery, muſt we preſently make us Gods to go before us? let us rather a little conſider what the Lord ſpeaks by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, chap.</hi> 50.11. <hi>behold all ye that kindle a fire, that compaſſe your ſelves about with ſparks, walk in the light of your fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kindled, this ſhall you have at mine hand, you ſhall lie down in ſorrow.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> for a while had left the Iſraelites, and was gone into the Mountain, <hi>Exodus</hi> 32. as you may read at large, it was a woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worſhip they performed to their god-calf, and ſurely <hi>Aaron.</hi> made a bad, bad exchange of his Prieſthood, in making an Altar, and proclaiming a holy day to it. I might inſtance in divers the like particulars, but I haſten; yet let me offer one thing to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which hath been a brand fixed on divers holy conſcientious perſons, that they are a people that deſpiſe the Miniſtery, and live above Ordinances; no certainly it is their grief and ſorrow of heart that they live below, and without them; and think you any perſons profeſſing Chriſt Jeſus, dare be ſuch rebells to him, as not to yeeld obedience to his commands, eſpecially when he tells them, <hi>that his yoke is eaſie, and his burden light,</hi> but blame them not for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Michals</hi> image to be <hi>Davids</hi> perſon, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.13. And now let us conſider what gracious promiſes are made to ſuch a people that ſee themſelves at ſo great a loſſe, read <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 50.10. <hi>Who is among you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voice of his ſervant,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 41.17, 18. <hi>Ch.</hi> 42.7.40.31.</note> that walketh in darkneſſe, and hath no light, let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God. chap,</hi> 30.18. <hi>and therefore will the Lord wait that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you, for the Lord is a God of Judgement, bleſſed are all they that wait for him, chap.</hi> 42.16. <hi>J will lead the blind by a way that they knew not, I will lead them in paths they have not known, I will make darkneſſe light before them, and crooked things ſtreight, theſe things will J do unto them, and not forſake them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And did not Chriſt come to fill the empty, to cloath the naked, to feed the hungry, and to ſet at liberty thoſe that were bound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Without controverſie, if ever we intend to be partakers of theſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180294:19"/>gifts before ſpoken, we muſt be firſt ſenſible of the want of them.</p>
            <p>Thus have <hi>I</hi> briefly and faithfully, to my own underſtanding, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you a ſmall taſt, which upon your farther conſideration I hope you will enlarge, and then <hi>I</hi> believe you will clearly diſcerne the ſhadow from the ſubſtance, which is to know the difference of the Baptiſm of Chriſt from <hi>Iohns,</hi> or of water from the Spirit, of ſpeaking from ſtudy, art, and learning, or from the gift of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to Prophecy, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. and of all the reſt of the gifts of the Spirit reckoned up in that chapter; and be aſſured it is a duty, that highly concernes us all, to try by Scripture the Spirits of thoſe we hear; and it was that which was commendable in the noble Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans, that they ſearched the Scriptures to ſee whether the things <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake were ſo or not, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. Nay it is the high commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which God himſelf gives to the Church of <hi>Epheſus, Revel.</hi> 2.2. <hi>I know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canſt not bear with them which are evill, and thou hast tried them which ſay they are Apostles, and are not, and haſt found them liers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for thoſe that deſire to know, and to be throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the practiſe, life, and power of Chriſtian Religion, may find it laid down in that incomparable Sermon preached by Chriſt himſelf in the Mountain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. to the 8. chapter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the former part of the 5: chapter, the qualifications of Saints are diſcovered to verſe 12. and that their Religion might not reſt in formality, he tells them verſe the 20. <hi>that except their righteouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, they ſhould not enter into the Kingdome of heaven;</hi> and to the end that they might not be unacquainted with the difference between a legall and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell obedience, he layes it forth in ſundry particulars unto the 28. ver. of 7. chap. wherein, as by a moſt perfect rule, we may be able to judge between Saints in word, and notion, and Saints in life and power; for underſtanding whereof, let us weigh and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one inſtance of many, where Chriſt tells the people ver. 43. of of 5. chap. ye have heard that it hath been ſaid of old, thou ſhalt love thy neighbour, and hate thine enemy, v. 44. but <hi>I</hi> ſay unto you <hi>love your enemies, bleſſe them which curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which perſecute you,</hi> v. 45. <hi>that you may be the children of your Father which is in heaven, for he maketh his Sun to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe on the evill and the good, and ſendeth rain on the juſt and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just; for if you love them which love you, what reward ſhall you have? do not the Publicans do the ſame?</hi> v. 47. <hi>and if you be friendly to your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180294:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>only, what ſingular thing do ye? do not even the Publicans like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe?</hi> if then this be the doctrine of Chriſt, and that which his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ought to practiſe, ſhall we not be ready to cry out with them, who then can be ſaved? the world at preſent is full of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and they full of fine words, ſuch as may juſtly be called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing words of vanity: but I deſire that we may all weigh our ſelves at this balance, and meaſure our ſelves by this Standard; ſo that when we find our ſelves qualified, as is here &amp; more at large in Scripture expreſſed, we may juſtly expect the performance of the promiſes, in being made partakers of the like gifts, as the believers were in the primitive time. And thus at preſent <hi>I</hi> have done with this, deſiring the Lord in mercy to give us a right underſtanding in all things:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THat the Gentleman and others may not be deceived, in thinking thoſe of the Pariſh, who were not Petitioners againſt him, are for him, in approving his book; if they think ſo, it is a groſſe miſtake, for to my knowledge divers of them did conclude it to be a great abuſe to the whole Pariſh; and when I ſpake of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering it, they did preſſe me exceedingly to it, not that I have any thing whereof to glory, but conſidering their earneſtneſſe, which I could not judge but to be in ſincerity of heart, it put me in mind of a paſſage, which when I was a School-Boy I then learned, and have not yet forgotten, it is <hi>Virgil Liber.</hi> 2 <hi>Aene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> where <hi>Aeneas</hi> (though very unwilling, yet being earneſtly entreated by <hi>Dido</hi> Queen of Carthage) makes relation of the Trojan warres, and give this reaſon, as you may read at large:
<q>
                  <l>Sed ſi tantus amor caſus cognoſcere noſtros,</l>
                  <l>Et breviter Trojae ſupremum audire laborem.</l>
                  <l>Quanquam Animus meminiſſe horret, luctuque refugit,</l>
                  <l>Incipiam, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall ſay the contrary; <hi>ità finem facio,</hi> that though I abhorred to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my mind in print, yet a juſt cauſe, and friends perſwaſions, were two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing arguments to do it, I ſhall only add one word more, and leave it to the conſideration of him that hath moſt right to it, (and the riddle may be unfolded hereafter) I can aſſure you, that in this diſcourſe, I have not to my knowledge made any falſe Muſter, neither have I, like ſome Commander, ſcrambled a pack of ſtrange faces together, to march through the City with as much confidence and little credit, as if they were his own liſted company.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:180294:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
